- This video is brought
to you by Squarespace,
an all-in-one platform
for building your brand
and growing your business online.
(edgy music)
Hello, my beautiful doves.
My name is Mina.
Welcome or welcome back,
and today we have a lot to discuss.
I'm mainly gonna be talking
about teenage girlhood,
internet aesthetic trends, and
what I call toxic femininity.
And if you're a little lost, don't worry.
It's all gonna make sense
by the end of this video,
but I do wanna start off by
talking about this one article
that went a little viral.
It was published on i-D Magazine.
It came out in June
and the article is
written by Roisin Lanigan.
I'm gonna read this very spicy excerpt.
"Hey, do you like
listening to Lana Del Rey?
"What about Fiona Apple,
"Mitski, Hole, Melanie Martinez, Marina?"
"Can you recite the cool girl speech
"from 'Gone Girl' verbatim?
"Do you love that one
Jacque Louis David piece,
"a 'Portrait of a Young Woman in White',
"not because you care about art,
"but because you like the
broken female protagonists
"of Otessa Moshfegh's literature?
"Do you have a favorite
Lisbon sister, and is it Lux?
"Are you still mourning
the loss of Tumblr?
"Do you like to read
Vladimir Nabokov's 'Lolita'?
"Do you enjoy Catholic iconography?
"Pressed to describe yourself
"or to have others describe you?
"Would you be comfortable with adjectives
"like toxic or manipulative?
"If the answers
(crowd cheers)
"to any of these questions is yes,
(bell chimes)
"then congratulations,
"you might be a femcel."
So this article got a lot of heat
on TikTok and Twitter
mostly for a lot of reasons.
Me personally, when I read
this article, the first thing
that came up into my head
was is this not just Tumblr
sad girl 2014 culture repackaged?
I mean, "Gone Girl" came out in 2012,
and I still remember people
making GIFs and graphics
using that monologue that she says.
- [Amy] Cool girl is hot.
Cool girl is game, cool girl is fun.
Cool girl never gets angry at her man.
- Lana Del Rey and Marina and the Diamonds
were the poster girls of
the Tumblr sad girl era,
and we didn't have "My Year
of Rest and Relaxation",
but the vibes were the same.
So none of this was seriously
shocking to me to read about.
Other people read this and
were understandably upset
by the categorization of femcel
and the implication that
listening to Fiona Apple
would bring you anywhere
close to that identifier.
And for anyone who doesn't know,
the term femcel is short for
female involuntary celibate,
AKA women who cannot
get laid not by choice.
And then there are just
people who are upset
about being categorized at all
for having particular interests.
Like just because you read
this one book and you like it,
or just because you like
this one female artist,
why do you have to be put and shoved
into this aesthetic category?
This TikTokker posted a
video complaining about it
with the caption, "I'll
never forgive you all
"for what you've done to Fiona Apple.
"She's not a femcel, that
is literally not a thing,
"and she's not a part of this stupid niche
"'Girl, Interrupted', red
scare, coquette, Lana Del Rey,
"Diet Coke, Kate Moss shit.
"Leave her alone and stop
grouping female artists
"into a box they never agreed to be in.
"She would those people, and I know it."
So I understand these
criticisms and complaints,
but as someone who's perpetually online,
and I mean that in the most
derogatory way possible,
I understand what Lanigan
was getting on about.
Because yes, there is
this growing subcommunity
on the internet, mostly on
TikTok and Tumblr and Twitter,
who are using femcel as
this aesthetic designator,
who've become somewhat obsessed
with categorizing themselves
based on specific niche interests.
It reminds me of the Substack essay
that my friend Rayne Fisher-Quann
wrote a few months ago.
She writes, "It's become
very common for women online
"to express their identities
"through an artfully curated list
"of the things they consume
or aspire to consume.
"And because young women
are conditioned to believe
"that their identities are defined
"almost entirely by their neuroses,
"these roundups of cultural
trends and authors du jour
"often implicitly serve to chicly signal
"one's mental illnesses to the public.
"One girl on your TikTok feed
"might be a self-described
Joan Didion/Eve Babitz/
"Marlboro Red/straight-cut
Levis/fleabag girl.
"This means
"she has depression.
(bell chimes)
"Another will call
herself a babydoll dress/
"Sylvia Plath/red scare/Miu
Miu/Lana Del Rey girl.
"Eating disorder.
"Or a green juice/claw
clip/Emma Chamberlain/
"yoga mat/podcast girl.
"Different eating disorder.
"The aesthetics of consumption
have in turn become a conduit
"to make the self more easily consumable,
"Your existence as a type of
girl has almost nothing to do
"with whether you actually read
Joan Didion or wear Mui Mui,
"and everything to do with
whether you want to be seen
"as the type of person who would."
So we're gonna be talking about
all this in just a minute,
but first a word from our sponsor.
On Squarespace, you have lots
of templates to choose from.
They've got a design
for just about everyone,
and even then you can
still customize your page
with backgrounds, colors,
and/or fonts like I did here.
And of course, Squarespace has
powerful built-in analytics
so you can see who's
visiting your site and more
with page views, traffic sources,
time on site, most read content,
audience geography, et cetera.
You can also use Squarespace
to set up a store
if you have things to sell.
They also let you put
in subscription plans
if you want to sell a service.
Check out squarespace.com for free trial,
and when you're ready to launch,
go to squarespace.com/minale
to save 10% off
your first purchase of
a website or domain.
(edgy music)
So the term that Lanigan uses to describe
this niche set of interests
or describe this new
aesthetic is femcel-core.
But before we can talk
about what femcel-core is,
we gotta start with the roots,
which are unfortunately incels.
The word incel, by the way,
stands for involuntary celibate,
AKA someone who cannot
get laid not by choice.
So in 1997, a Canadian woman
who goes by Alana and nothing else,
she has kept her identity
mostly anonymous,
she had started dating
and was having trouble with relationships,
so she started this website
called Alana's Involuntary
Celibate Project
for anyone else who was also struggling
with the romance department.
It was a simple website
where she posted articles,
ran a mailing list, and
then evolved into a forum
where people would talk
about being lonely.
Alana says, "There was
probably a bit of anger
"and some men were a bit clueless
"about how women are
unique individual humans,
"but in general it was a supportive place.
"The word incel used to
mean anybody of any gender
"who was lonely, had never had sex,
"or who hadn't had a
relationship in a long time."
Fast forward to 2014, a
22-year-old man named Elliot Rodger
went on a shooting and stabbing spree
in Isla Vista, California,
killing six people
and injuring 14 before offing himself.
It was revealed that before his death
he had distributed a 141 page document
about his hatred towards women
that was caused by his intense frustration
of being a virgin.
And then in 2018,
25-year-old Alec Minassian
drove his van into a
crowded sidewalk in Toronto,
killing 10 people and injuring 16.
After the attack, he told investigators
that he was an incel and that his actions
were a revenge plot over him
not being able to get laid.
The incel community has thus developed
in the worst way possible from
being a fringe internet group
to a recognized terrorist threat.
So we compare them to femcels.
The only real shared thing is their belief
that they cannot have sex
or cannot get into romantic relationships
because of their looks or personality.
And even though a lot of
people feel this type of way,
at least during one point in
their lives, femcels believe
there's something
significantly wrong with them
that makes them different
from other women.
According to the now
defunct Reddit thread,
trufemcels, "to be a femcel,
"you have to have defects that must exceed
"those of normal women
"and exist in a much more severe form."
As MEL Magazine puts it,
"Femcels were dealt a shitty
hand, the sentiment goes,
"and the only way out of the
lonely hellscapes they live in
"is to ascend, femcel
speak for get hotter."
Since the Reddit thread has been banned,
it's difficult to mine it for content
unless you know how to use
internet archive tools,
but from articles that I've read,
it sounds like unlike incel forms,
femcels are nonviolent for the most part.
Like there might be some fringe person
who's writing something truly disturbing,
but for the most part, most of the content
was focused on the women's
unhappiness with themselves.
And unfortunately this rhetoric
is actually how most women tend to feel
when navigating romantic spheres.
Tracy Moore did an
investigation on nice girls
and found that women, most women
who blame their lack of sex
or relationships on their appearance
actually feel embarrassed or sorry
for inconveniencing the people
that they find attractive.
That's not to say that there
are absolutely no problems
in the femcel community, though.
Lorelei Alverson researched femcel forums
and found that, "Despite several members
"identifying as people of color,
"the vast majority of
users across femcel forums
"are white and leveraged
this whiteness in disputes."
There are also a lot
of transphobic femcels
who express anger towards trans women
who are able to get facial
feminization surgery
covered by their health insurance.
And I think even people who
are not outwardly transphobic,
the lingo that's used among femcels,
like femcels speak and the
assumptions that they have
about women tend to fall into
this gender essentialist,
like there are only two genders mindset,
which ends up becoming a breeding ground
for transphobic trains of thought.
So what I just described to you all
is what I consider to
be traditional femcels,
traditional in the sense
that in the past couple years or so,
there's been a different
community of women
who identify themselves as
femcels, but are so far removed
from all the lore that
I just talked about.
And these femcels, which
I'll call modern femcels
to be less confusing,
is what that i-D article
was talking about.
The article even clarifies,
"The social media femcels of today
"use the term less as an indicator
"of how much sex they're unable to have
"and more as a way to express
their personality traits
"that are perceived as
pathetic or manipulative
"or toxic in some way.
"They do so unapologetically,
"romanticizing these
stereotypical femcel traits
"in the process."
Modern femcels mostly exist
on Twitter, TikTok, Tumblr,
and they make sad
aesthetic Spotify playlists
titled Female Manipulator Anthems
and Songs for your Fleabag Era.
By the way, I've like
referenced fleabag eras
in previous videos, but
not yet in this video,
and basically "Fleabag"
is a TV show that centers
around this pretty problematic
female protagonist,
and the term fleabag era refers to anyone
who is essentially
embracing chaos and mess
to deal with trauma
rather than seeking help.
(operatic music)
(car horn honks)
Lanigan writes, "New
femcels have flourished
"on popular social media platforms,
"where it can be communicated
not through tortured posts
"about being overlooked
by men and self-hatred,
"but rather through a post-ironic,
"self-conscious embrace of
aesthetic feminine toxicity.
"It's not femcel for these
women, it's femcel-core."
For example, one 19-year-old
Tumblr user named Hannah
who regularly uses the
hashtag #femcel said,
"I just thought the word was funny
"and maybe even a little shocking.
"I knew it would get people's attention.
"Most of my posts are ironic.
"I've been in a relationship
"with my boyfriend for two years."
Similarly, a 22-year-old
TikTokker named Alexandra Carmona
admitted her female
manipulator content is ironic.
She told Insider that,
"It's not about promoting
actual manipulation.
"It's about calling ourselves out
"and coping with her own issues
by making a joke out of it."
So aesthetically I've
noticed a lot of overlap
and a lot of lime blurring
between these femcels,
these modern femcels, the
coquette girls, and ballet-core.
I've done a whole video on ballet-core,
but for coquette, girls who partake in it
flock to frilly slip
dresses, hair ribbons,
thigh-high socks, Mary Janes,
tight fitting tank tops,
cropped cardigans, cheeky
slogans on baby tees,
and overall pastel colors
and lace trimmings.
Popular aesthetic icons
shared by all three subgroups
include Lana Del Rey,
particularly at the
beginning of her career,
Nina Sayers from "Black Swan",
Angelina Jolie's character
in "Girl, Interrupted",
Jennifer from "Jennifer's Body",
"Gone Girl", and of course
models and actresses
that have heroin chic
or waif-like body types,
including Lily Rose-Depp, young Kate Moss,
Bella Hadid, and Mia Goth.
A lot of these girls
also refer to themselves
as girlbloggers,
AKA girly girls who blog
about being a girl's girl
who have usernames like
@diorwaif or @cocainebambi,
who post grainy GIFs
of blonde '90s models,
Mui Mui ballet flats,
young Natalie Portman,
Lana Del Rey lyrics, Patrick Bateman,
and memes that hint out or
explicitly state mental illness.
There's a lot of romanticization
about being pretty and mentally unstable,
but that being okay because
you're still pretty.
And terminology like pilled, maxxing,
being in your whatever, whatever era,
and esoteric get tossed around.
There's also very unique turn of phrasing
that these girls use.
Biz Sherbert describes it in
their article on girlblogging.
"I'm unstable in a 'Black
Swan', 'The Virgin Suicides',
"nepotism baby, cool girl monologue,
"Sylvia Plath, Brittany Murphy,
"'Fatal Attraction' kind of way.
"A girlblogger's frequent lines of texts
"rub together into an inner monologue
"that looms over all her posts.
"This diary voice, psychologically charged
"and often bitchy like the
writing on a bathroom stall,
"is what separates the girlblogger
"from an impersonal moodboarder
"with a similar taste for girly things."
(edgy music)
- [Man] You Can't keep
getting away with this.
- So just to recap on what was happening
on Tumblr around 2012 to 2015,
a popular subculture on
Tumblr revolved heavily
around Lana Del Rey GIFs and lyrics,
black and white photos with
sad captions overlaid on them.
and cigarette self-harm and drug motifs.
And who can forget the hashtag
#prettywhenyou cry selfies.
This was all part of a movement
now known as the sad girl era.
Rosemary Kirton defined a sad girl for i-D
"as one who listens to
better music than you
"and might spend her alone time
"watching French films from the '60s
"or angsty TV shows from the '90s."
But even before the 2010s,
the sad girl was not a new phenomenon.
Like think of "Romeo + Juliet",
think of Ophelia from "Hamlet",
think of "Jane Eyre".
And yes, there were
always shared aesthetics
and films and songs that
sad girls leaned onto
as Rayne puts it, "To chicly
signal one's mental illness,"
but I will say it wasn't as self-aware
or self-commodifying as
the girlbloggers are today.
Sad girls mostly posted
stream of conscious thoughts
into the void on Tumblr,
and our collective
interest in Arctic Monkeys
and Marina and the Diamonds
music felt more like coincidence
than a calculated attempt
to aestheticize our own identities.
At this time, journalists
were releasing think pieces
about how the sad girl aesthetic movement
romanticized clinical
depression and eating disorders,
which I definitely agree that it was.
I don't think it was intentional.
Like I don't think any movie
director or any songwriter
was explicitly trying to
de-legitimize mental illness
with their music, but
that's just what happened.
And it definitely didn't help
that being sad was considered cool,
and so a lot of teenage girls
who probably weren't actually battling
with serious mental illnesses
kind of induced traits
of those mental illnesses
within themselves as an attempt to fit in.
The sad girl movement
wasn't just pervasive on Tumblr, though.
They were brands that were
selling pins, tote bags,
and necklaces with
phrases like Sad Girl Club
and other slogans on them.
Hannah May wrote for HelloGiggles,
"Even more disturbing than teens
using depression to be cool
"is the possibility of
companies marketing depression
"to those teens to make a quick buck."
Granted, I think one of
the main issues these days
is how out of hand consumerism has gotten,
and consumerism is
unfortunately a byproduct
of making everything into
different aesthetics.
I asked what people
thought about this topic
on my Instagram Stories a couple days ago,
and one person said, "I feel
like now more than ever,
"these aesthetics are so intertwined
with consumerism/trend cycles."
Similarly, another person said,
"We can let women be angry
"without attaching an
aesthetic/a title to it."
And yet another person said,
"I think it's really
fun to be in a community
"with lots of other girls who
like the same things as me,
"but it can also be really exclusionary
"and breed a pick me-esque mindset
"if you aren't as indie/enjoy
too many mainstream things
"or even dress somewhat basic."
I think these are all very valid points.
I also think that they are points
that were valid back in the 2010s.
If anyone remembers, like,
the whole hipster trend--
- Just so you know,
a macchiato is a shot of espresso
with a little foam on top.
It's not a giant latte
slathered in whipped cream
with caramel squeezed all over it.
- Hey, what band is this?
- You've never heard of it.
- To really qualify as a hipster,
it wasn't enough to just
like the same things
as everyone else or have
the same kind of ideology.
Like, you had to get the square glasses,
you had to wear the infinity scarves,
you had to have some mustache
motifs somewhere on your body
or else your friends were probably like,
are you really a hipster?
And God forbid if you wanna listen
to Justin Bieber every once in a while.
The difference between then and now
is obviously social media,
because rather than just having
to gain approval from your
local group of friends,
the internet is so global and
now there's so many people
who belong to this community
who you are connected with
and who you are constantly
seeking approval from,
not to mention the endless
content-focused moodboards
that give you new consumers' ideas
of how to gain people's approval.
But the biggest problem I have
with commodifying sadness,
even back in like the 2010s,
is that it made wallowing in sadness cool
and getting help uncool.
Similarly, in the femcel
girlblogger subculture,
by making female hysteria
and mental illness aesthetic,
it discourages young women
from wanting to get help.
22-year-old TikTokker
Jules Johnson told Insider
that she finds the trend
nihilistic and hollow.
She said, "In the female
manipulator space,
"there's a lot of focus
on getting back at men
"when you could direct that energy
"towards loving other women."
But anyways, I think the
Tumblr girl ideology redux
was kind of inevitable,
considering the style itself
is getting a renewed appreciation
with the tag #2014tumblr
having over 215 million views on TikTok.
Femcel-core also champions
the thin body type,
which is being echoed in the mainstream
with low rise pants and skirts
coming back in full force,
and even Kim Kardashians
slimming down her booty
in the past several months.
- I think some of you guys are forgetting
what Kim K used to look like.
Look at the, look at the mass, okay?
This about 40 pounds ass gone.
- Because of how influential
the Kardashians are,
and because they were kind of
the ones to popularize BBLs
in the past 10 years to begin with,
a lot of people feel like
them shrinking their asses
is a sign that the BBL era is over.
BBL, by the way, stands
for Brazilian butt lift,
which is a very dangerous procedure
that shifts the fat in your
stomach into your booty
to give you a more curvaceous figure.
Even without the Kardashians' involvement,
it might just be the natural
course of body of type trends
that's dictating this shift in silhouette,
because as we all know,
very unfortunately throughout
the course of history,
women's silhouettes have been trends.
It's dipped from curvy to
skinny, to curvy to skinny,
and we've just been curvy
in the last 10 years
and I guess it's time
to go back to skinny.
Obviously I think BBLs and
kind of escaping that phase
is a good thing, because BBLs
are incredibly dangerous.
Like you can literally
die on the operating table
for getting one, but I don't think
going the other end of
the spectrum is better,
because I grew up in the '90s and 2000s.
Like, everyone had an eating disorder
because of how skinny
everyone in the media was.
- Do you know what really just kills me
about this whole thing
is the clothes that you are gonna get?
I mean, you don't deserve them.
You eat carbs, for Christ's sake.
(edgy music)
- Even though I think
it's somewhat natural
for girls to feel very angsty
or to feel a certain way
about their place in society,
I also think that there have
been movements and trends
that have occurred in
the past five years or so
that has also contributed
to the rise of femcel-core.
For example, during the first
two years of the pandemic,
there was a major societal
trend towards self-improvement.
A lot of people felt pressured
to utilize their time in
isolation productively,
either by reading as
many books as possible,
listening to as many podcasts as possible,
watching as many movies as possible,
learning new skills,
getting fit,
dieting, you name it.
The desire for self-improvement gave rise
to the that girl trend,
which was a major trend
on TikTok and Instagram
and revolved around girls
who essentially had their lives together,
or at least looked like they
had their lives together.
These girls would film
themselves waking up at 5:00 AM,
going on runs, doing
Pilates in the morning,
drinking green smoothies,
wearing beige athleisure sets,
and meditating and journaling,
gratitude journaling regularly,
just doing everything that we feel
we are supposed to do for our
mental and physical health,
all while looking absolutely amazing.
While some people were inspired
by the whole that girl trend
to get their life together,
a lot of people also felt very uninspired
because they felt like the trend
was inaccessible for people
who were not white, skinny, or
at least upper middle class.
Laura Pitcher wrote an
article on that girl
for I-D last year,
noting that it was a rebranding
of girl boss culture.
"Similar to other fitness
videos on social media,
"being 'that girl' means
encompassing a life
"based on mainstream notions of wellness.
"However, there's bizarrely no end goal.
"No marathon you train up to,
"no reason to wake up at 5:00 AM,
"other than that it seems more efficient."
And this is just a general
thing with our society,
like a general problem, where
a lot of our health goals
are focused on aesthetic motivations
rather than scientific ones.
For example, a lot of dieting books talk
about how to lose weight,
but not why you should want to lose weight
because our dieting culture
revolves around looking thin,
not being healthier for
whatever your body type allows.
It actually is a healthy
thing for their body to do,
but just because they feel
like it's more aesthetically productive.
So because there's a lot of pressure
to constantly be improving yourself,
it makes sense that there
would inevitably be a movement
that pushes back against
that kind of rhetoric.
Jia Tolentino wrote in
her book "Trick Mirror",
"The ideal woman has always
been conceptually overworked,
"an inorganic thing
engineered to look natural.
"Figuring out how to 'get
better' at being a woman
"is a ridiculous and
often amoral project."
A lot of girls have taken this desire
to not be perfect to the extreme, though.
Lanigan also wrote another
article earlier this year
talking about feral girl summer,
which explored the part satirical
but part very true desire
to just be imperfect.
The ultimate power of
being in your fleabag era
or being a femcel or
embracing a feral girl summer
is that you're allegedly self-aware.
You're aware that womanhood is oppressive,
and rather than trying to lean
in and hustle 'til you die,
you've just decided to give
up, sit back, and be cynical.
It's ironically kind of
I'm not like the other girls ideology,
despite its heavy reliance
on feminine aesthetics.
I don't think having a
little nihilistic era
every so often in your life
is a bad thing inherently,
but I think it can be
dangerous if it goes to extreme
or if it becomes so mainstream
that it takes up valuable
conversation space
for actually productive feminist action.
As Hailey McNiff writes,
"If women are drolly accepting their pain
"as inborn and inevitable,
"there may be an empowering
sense of numbness
"in fully embracing that pain,
"in running headlong into it yourself
"and even bringing others down
with you if you so choose."
It's definitely frustrating,
and one of the number one complaints
I got from my Instagram
Stories were women saying
that the movement is just not reasonable
for a woman of color or a
girl of color to partake in.
Aurora Muir wrote a great article on this
and how disassociating
to the world's problems
keeps oppressors comfortably empowered.
She writes, "These white
dissociating feminists
"are holding up their hands and saying,
"'There is nothing I can do about it.
"The world is just too
fucked up for me to help.
"I'm gonna have to lie down.'"
She also offers the alternative
of community care and love.
"Being a person is fucking hard
"and it's fucking horrible sometimes.
"But I'd like to give
our daughters and sisters
"a world they want to be a part of,
"where they can laugh and love
as opposed to one so bitter
"they must wither themselves away
"in an effort to spare
themselves from it."
I don't think all modern
femcels are bitter, by the way.
I think some of them have derived
some kind of sick pleasure
in being stuck in the system,
kind of like a Stockholm syndrome,
but I do agree with Muir overall.
I think a lot can be
said about how nihilism
can numb us from making any progress.
And rather than just flipping
the script on girl bosses
and being like, girls don't
actually have to lean in
and work super hard and be the best,
it's worth just having more
productive conversations
on how we can make girlhood and womanhood
more bearable and even enjoyable
without being self-destructive.
But you know, what do I know?
I was a teenage girl once, too.
Okay, everyone, that's
all I have for today.
Thank you so much for tuning in.
Please let me know in the
comments what you think
about toxic femininity and all the things
that I've discussed today.
I would love to hear your input.
I feel like it's one of those topics
that has become way more
in vogue to discuss about,
and therefore has piqued my interest
because I keep seeing new and
interesting takes about it.
And I'm just like very
interested, I guess,
in women's studies
because I am one. (laughs)
Thank you for sticking around.
I hope you have a lovely rest of your day
and I'll see you next time.
Bye.
(blows kiss)